<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Algorithmic Assertions - Craig Gidney's Computer Science Blog</title>
        <description>A blog about computer science, software engineering, quantum computing, mathematical puzzles, and so forth.</description>
        <link>http://algassert.com</link>
        <atom:link href="http://algassert.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
            <item>
                <title>Canonicalizing H+S+CNOT+T Circuits</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;A problem I&amp;#39;ve been interested in lately is &amp;quot;how do I prove I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; some number of T gates for a circuit?&amp;quot;. As part of thinking about that, I wanted some way to systematically search through circuit space. But just iterating over all the possible combinations and permutations of gates...</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2018 10:10:10 -0800</pubDate>
                <link>http://algassert.com/post/1801</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://algassert.com/post/1801</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Why will quantum computers be slow?</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Large error corrected quantum computers are many years away. Despite that, we know the factors that will decide how fast (or slow) these hypothetical machines will run. They are: being able to hold the computation in the first place, distilling states fast enough to feed the computation, waiting for measurements...</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 10:10:10 -0800</pubDate>
                <link>http://algassert.com/post/1800</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://algassert.com/post/1800</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>A Classical Delayed Choice Experiment</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The delayed choice quantum eraser (DCQE) is a widely misunderstood experiment. The internet is full of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/Does-the-delayed-choice-quantum-eraser-experiment-prove-that-time-is-just-an-illusion&quot;&gt;questions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.louisdelmonte.com/a-classic-time-travel-paradox-double-slit-experiment-demonstrates-reverse-causality/&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KnpCH9VRvPg&quot;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://io9.gizmodo.com/an-experiment-that-might-let-us-control-events-millions-1525760859&quot;&gt;articles&lt;/a&gt; that seem to think the DCQE is definitive proof of time travel or some other nonsense. But, from the perspective of quantum information...</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 05:10:20 -0800</pubDate>
                <link>http://algassert.com/post/1720</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://algassert.com/post/1720</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Proxy Phasing and Computed Phasing</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post, I&amp;#39;m going to explain a trick for phasing quantum states in a convenient and flexible way. Basically, the trick involves preparing ancilla qubits to act as proxies for the states you want to target, then phasing those ancilla. Thus the name &amp;quot;proxy phasing&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll start simple, but...</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2017 10:10:10 -0800</pubDate>
                <link>http://algassert.com/post/1719</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://algassert.com/post/1719</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Shor's Quantum Factoring Algorithm</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, I wrote a post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://twistedoakstudios.com/blog/Post2644_grovers-quantum-search-algorithm&quot;&gt;how Grover&amp;#39;s quantum search algorithm works&lt;/a&gt;. I think it went over quite well. I&amp;#39;ve heard from several people that it was the first time they &amp;quot;got&amp;quot; anything about quantum computing. Today I want to do the same thing, but with...</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2017 06:10:20 -0700</pubDate>
                <link>http://algassert.com/post/1718</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://algassert.com/post/1718</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Breaking Down the Quantum Swap</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Suppose you have two qubits. For evocative purposes, suppose you&amp;#39;re literally holding them as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloch_sphere&quot;&gt;balls&lt;/a&gt; in your hands: one in the left hand, and one in the right hand. Your goal is to swap the qubits, so that your right hand ends up holding a qubit storing the state...</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 13:10:20 -0700</pubDate>
                <link>http://algassert.com/post/1717</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://algassert.com/post/1717</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Visualizing 2-Qubit Entanglement</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the annoying things about quantum computing is that it&amp;#39;s not very amenable to visualization. We do have a great way to draw the state of one qubit, i.e. the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloch_sphere&quot;&gt;Bloch sphere&lt;/a&gt;, but it doesn&amp;#39;t work very well for more qubits. This makes the Bloch sphere a double-edged...</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2017 13:10:20 -0700</pubDate>
                <link>http://algassert.com/post/1716</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://algassert.com/post/1716</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>My Second Paper: A Slightly Smaller Surface Code S Gate</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I was trying to learn more about the surface code by reading through the 2012 paper &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1208.0928&quot;&gt;Surface codes: Towards practical large-scale quantum computation&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; by Austin Fowler et al. The paper is great; it uses lots of concepts and ways of thinking about quantum states that I&amp;#39;m not used...</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 20:10:20 -0700</pubDate>
                <link>http://algassert.com/post/1715</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://algassert.com/post/1715</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Reversible Computation isn't Free</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landauer%27s_principle&quot;&gt;Landauer&amp;#39;s principle&lt;/a&gt; puts a lower limit on the cost of irreversible computations. Basically: clearing a bit requires a minimum amount of energy (that depends on the ambient temperature), so a computation must consume an amount of energy proportional to how many bits it clears. (The energy efficiency of current...</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2017 13:10:20 -0700</pubDate>
                <link>http://algassert.com/post/1714</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://algassert.com/post/1714</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Impractical Experiments #4: High Powered Phase Estimation</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/post/1710&quot;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I explained how using quantum phase estimation on an operation can provide a mechanism for applying fractional powers of that operation. The basic idea being that the register containing the phase estimation acts as an index into the eigenspaces of the operation, allowing you phase...</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 13:10:20 -0700</pubDate>
                <link>http://algassert.com/post/1713</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://algassert.com/post/1713</guid>
            </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
